Don't cry.
不可以哭的
Hey!
喂
Seems that Suo-sama was called by the presbytery.
听说苏澳哥哥被长老会叫去了
So finally they started to do something.
终于有动静了么
Translator
翻
ssnake
译
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
ssnake
Silence and melody, and the transient lives of Shirushi
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
时 间 轴
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
If you have been living on the land, on the sea of sand
如果是在这沙海之上  生活下去
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
In a sinned world, we have heard the whale's lied
在罪业重重的世界里  我们曾侧耳倾听鲸鱼的歌唱…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
Our fate and our emotions, my beloved children
不论命运  还是感情  亲爱的孩子们哟
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
Towards the future, go ahead
向着未来  向着前方
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
If you can be our guide
只要有你指引前路
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
Thousands of words, leaving for the fantasy lands
万千寄语  向着空想的彼岸
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
Steering towards the opposite
相信信念调转方向
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
Thousands of songs, they are the ballads of the sea of sand
万千欢声  是沙海的歌谣
F
雪 飘 工 作 室
L
雪 飘 工 作 室
Suo,
苏澳
you have been appointed as the new chief of the mud whale.
任命你为泥鲸的新任首长
I accept it respectfully.
谨遵诏命
You looks so bad.
你脸色好差
Wash your clothes, it'll disturb our people.
你的衣服也去洗洗 会让大家动摇的
If you can't get the dirt off, we will provide you a new one.
要是洗不干净 就给你发件新衣服
It is not dirt...
这不是不干净的东西
It is Sami's...
这是 莎米的…
Oh dear...
哎呀哎呀
You are still a child.
你也还是个孩子啊
Suo.
苏澳
Neli...
奈莉…
Sorry...
对不起
You can't cry forever, Suo.
没时间让你一直哭哭啼啼的了 苏澳
Right.
是啊
We are also in pain.
我们也很难过的
But there is something you have to do.
但是 有件事情交给你
It's the first and last mission for you, as the chief.
这是你作为首长 「最初也是最后」的使命
It was something decided by all the presbyters a few minutes ago.
这是刚才长老会全体成员一致通过的决议
We have decided
决定让泥鲸
to sink the mud whale into the sea of sand.
沉入沙海
What do you mean?
这是什么意思
Then where should we go?
那我们该何去何从
Where should we live?
我们该住在哪儿
We shall
让我们
suicide in the sand, together with the mud whale.
与泥鲸一起葬身沙海
We hope you can guide us
作为最后的首长
to death of proud, as the last chief.
愿你指引大家光荣地死
This is your first and last mission.
这就是你 最初也是最后的使命
Why...
为什么…
Why must everybody die!
为什么大家非死不可
Those who attacked us,
那些袭击我们的人
were from where used to be our mother country.
来自我们的祖国
Eh...
诶…
Our ancestors were exiled to the sea of sand for their guilt.
我们的先祖因为某项罪名被流放沙海
The exile is continued till now.
一直流放至今
And now,
如今
they have decided to execute us.
他们决定处死我们
Those soldiers were intended
那些士兵
to massacre all the people here in mud whale.
本意就是要把我们泥鲸的人民杀得一个不剩
Their purpose is not invasion,
他们的目的并非侵略
but execution.
而是处刑
There is no way to avoid it.
这是我们所无从回避的
Nobody want to see our people be killed miserably
谁都不想看到泥鲸的子民
in the mud whale.
被残忍杀死
For our pride, we shall go to that world ourselves elegantly.
为了保护大家的尊严 只能在那之前安详地踏上不归之路
Byakuroku-sama?
毕雅库洛库爷爷？
Our father... I don't want it.
父亲啊… 不想啊
I don't want to be killed!
不想被杀啊
I don't want to be sunk either!
但也不想淹死啊
He lost himself for a long time.
他已经失去了自我
Take Byakuroku-sama to his room.
送毕雅库洛库爷爷回房里去
The eldest presbyter!
最长老先生
Fine. It will be fine.
没关系… 没关系的
I will not let you die unreasonably like Sami and Taisha-sama.
我不会让你像莎米和台霞姐姐那样 莫名其妙地死去的
Suo!
苏澳！
I don't want anyone to die anymore!
我不会让任何人去送死的！
There must be a way for everybody to survive!
一定有着让大家都活下去的方法！
Yes...
对了…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
You should ask our father, Fallaina.
去问父亲吧 去问「法莱那」就好了
Fallaina knows everything.
法莱那他什么都知道
Fallaina? The word the girl from that island said...
法莱那？ 岛上那个少女说过的…
Doesn't it mean the mud whale?
那难道不是指泥鲸吗？
Suo! Stop!
苏澳！ 快住口！
You don't need to know it!
你不需要知道！
Tell me please, the eldest presbyter.
请告诉我 最长老先生
What does it mean?
那到底是什么
What does it mean exactly by Fallaina...
法莱那到底是指什么…
I should restrain him in such a situation...
出现这样的情况就把他抓起来
I supposed you have told me this.
是这么回事吧
I should do it, right?
没问题吧？
Ye... Yes.
嗯 没问题…
We told you in advance.
我们之前就是这么说的
Strengthen the guard of the underground too, our Captain.
地下的警备也拜托了 团长
How can he say something like that...
没想到那孩子竟然会这样说…
He is still young.
他还小
We can't blame him.
没办法
We have to change our mood and proceed our task.
我们得整理一下心情继续向前迈进
Come on, let's start the preparation.
快 开始准备
Neli...
奈莉
What are you writing?
这个 写的是什么啊？
Don... Don't read it!
别… 别看！
Don't worry, I'm not literate.
没关系 我不识字的
Also...
而且啊…
If you don't want other read, don't scribble here.
要是不想被人看见就别在这里涂涂画画啊
I was told by Tobikko,
我听托比仔说了
that you succeeded in beating the enemy with your thymia.
thymia
Only you and Oni have succeeded
那时候能反击他们的
in fighting back against those guys.
只有你和欧尼俩
How did you make it, destroyer!
没想到毁灭者这么能干！
You are so great!
你好厉害啊！
Stop it.
别说了
I haven't done anything.
我什么都没能做到
That's why Sami died.
所以莎米才死了
I didn't fight back against somebody or beat somebody.
反击谁干掉谁什么的
And don't tell me that anymore.
我不想再听到了
That's why you are scribbling your excuses on the wall?
所以就把这些借口往墙上瞎写？
Although Samikko died,
虽然莎米子死了
you saved the kiddies of Tobikko, didn't you?
但是托比仔家的小家伙们不是得救了
Take your credit,
这是你的功劳
and be proud!
挺直胸膛了
I can't be as easygoing as you.
我没法像你这样满不在乎啊
Don't call me you, call me Miss Ginshu!
怎么叫我的 叫「银淑姐姐」！
It doesn't matter how I call you, right?
怎么叫都无所谓不是
It matters!
才不是！
It's important how you call me,
怎么称呼别人可重要了
cuz it shows how you think about me!
这代表着你怎么看待那个人
I will teach you how to use thymia,
我来教你怎么用情念力
so you can fight against those guys when they come again.
让你在他们下次来的时候能上阵迎战
Therefore, call me Miss Ginshu in respect!
所以毕恭毕敬地叫我「银淑姐姐」
Now, call me!
快 叫声姐姐！
Miss... Ginshu...
银淑… 姐姐
That's right!
这就对了！
Do your best, Chakky!
加油啊 查奇！
My name's Chakuro...
我叫查克罗
Sucks, it doesn't matter!
管它呢 怎么都无所谓嘛
OK, see you again, Chakky!
那 再见啦 查奇
Chakuro!
查克罗！
Neli?
奈莉？
You can't climb from here.
这边上不来的
Go around from behind.
从后面绕过来
Chakuro.
查克罗
It's so beautiful...
好漂亮呢…
But do you know why the world is so beautiful?
你知道为什么这个世界这么漂亮吗
The souls of the people who have lived here so far,
因为过去生活在此的人们
are melted into the world.
魂魄都溶化在了这个世界
For example, you can see it here...
瞧 这里也有…
What is it?
这是… 什么
This is...
这是…
These people...
这些人是…
Sami!
莎米
Sami, you are alive...
莎米… 你还活着吗…
Listen, I wanted...
那个 我啊…
I wanted to be Chakuro's bride!
想当查克罗的新娘子的
Sami...
莎米…
Wait, Sami!
等等… 莎米！
I love you too!
我也喜欢你
Even if we Shirushi are short-lived,
哪怕我们「印」的人生苦短
we may become bedridden and die very soon,
哪怕我们很快就会动弹不得 不久人世
but it's fine if you can be with me.
只要能跟你一起我就满足了
Even a small wish like this can't be fulfilled...
要是连这样小小的愿望都不能得到满足
Then I'm no longer reluctant to leave this world!
那我 对这个世界已经不再留恋了
Take me there!
带我去你那边吧
That's impossible.
这可不行
Since Chakuro has a role to play here.
因为查克罗还有查克罗要做的工作
Wait!
等等
Yes...
是的…
You are the recorder of the truth.
你是真实的记录者
Taisha-sama...
台霞阿姨…
The mud whale will be destroyed if you don't do anything.
这样下去泥鲸将会覆灭
Then nobody can know the truth of this island,
这个岛的真实将无人知晓
since we will all disappear.
而我们则就此消失
You must see everything with your eyes.
你一定要亲眼目睹这一切
It should not be the end of this island...
这个岛还没有走到…
Should not...
还没有走到终点
Wahh!
哇！
Oni!
欧尼
Suo...
苏澳
Lykos!
黎可斯！
Neli, have you seen...
奈莉… 刚才那是…
Hey, haven't you seen Sami and others?
呐 你也看到莎米她们了吗？
Have you seen Suo and Lykos are suffering?
苏澳和黎可斯的痛苦…
You are able to feel the hearts of people brilliantly.
你能深刻地感受他人的心灵
Maybe you think that is useless,
或许你觉得这什么都做不到
but if you don't connect everyone together,
但唯有你能够联系起大家
it will be our end.
否则一切都将终结
Chakuro!
查克罗
Help me!
救救大家
I accidentally found that
我不小心知道了
the presbyters is trying to sink the mud whale together with us!
长老会他们
Suo was opposed,
反对的苏澳
but he is arrested in the internal area now!
已经被关在体内区域了
Really?
这是真的吗？
In order to save everybody,
要想救大家
you need to free a person's mind first.
必须先让一个人的心灵得到解放
Please go for her.
快去帮帮她吧
Lykos?
黎可斯？
Are you crying?
你在哭吗
The ship which I was in,
我在的那艘船
was intended to attack Fallaina.
本来是来袭击法莱那的
We knew nothing about you.
大家什么都不知道
We were told that this island is a hell.
只是被灌输了这里是地狱之岛
But it was us who takes the hell here...
明明是我们
You get to have so many emotions now!
已经能够表现出这么丰富的感情了啊
Don't worry.
别担心
I have seen your heart twice.
我已经两次窥见了你的心灵了
I trust you, Lykos.
我相信黎可斯
By the way, Lykos,
呐 黎可斯
I need your help.
想请你帮帮我
We will be sunk into the sea of sand.
就这样下去大家都会沉入沙海
What should I do?
我该做什么
But I can hardly believe it.
但是真不敢相信呢
We can't even control the destination of the mud whale.
明明连泥鲸的去向都谁也控制不了
How did the presbytery know
长老会是怎么知道
the method to sink the mud whale.
让泥鲸沉没的方法的
I think I know it.
我 或许知道
Is there anywhere
在这个岛上
that nobody has ever entered in the island?
有没有一个谁都没有进去过的地方？
The internal area! The underground!
「体内区域」！ 地下
Though a few parts are used as the prison,
虽然一部分被用作监狱
there are secret spaces where nobody can enter.
但还有其他谁也没进去过的秘密空间
Underground...
地下…
Lykos!
黎可斯！
Ah!
哇
It pains...
啊痛…
Suo is also arrested underground, I think.
现在苏澳应该也被关在地下
He also need our help.
也得救出他来
Pick up the useless arrows carefully!
用不了的箭要好好分出来
Yep~
是～
A week will soon be passed.
七天而已 转眼的事
We have to be prepared for their attacks.
要准备好应对那帮家伙的袭击
Yes yes.
是是～
Do you really understand?
你真的明白么
Oops.
啊呀
Pain!
啊痛
Masoo, are you OK?
玛索 你没事吧
Ah, yeah.
啊 没事
Masoo!
玛索
Nezu! Lo!
涅兹 洛
It's Chakuro!
查克罗啊
We are gathering the weapons for hunting right now.
我们正在收集狩猎用的武器
You shouldn't do that now!
不是干这个的时候了
What? Sink the mud whale?
你说什么 泥鲸要沉没了？
So I need your hands.
所以 想借你们一臂之力
Hey wait a moment, it's a mess...
喂等等 这到底什么跟什么…
If you are to go oppose the presbytery,
要反对长老会的话
you will have to fight against the vigilante group.
也就是说得跟警备团干仗了啊
The vigilante group?
警备团？
You really think we can do it with these members?
我们这几个人又能干什么
Kicha,
绮茶
Where's... Oni?
欧尼… 呢？
Oni!
欧尼
Cooperate with us!
帮帮我们
What the hell you are!
你搞什么啊
The mud whale is going to sink into the sea of sand...
这样下去泥鲸就要沉入沙海…
Help us please!
拜托了！
We have been trapped in such a narrow island.
被关在这么一个狭小的岛上
When we finally found the would outside,
本以为好不容易发现了外面的世界
we are trampled by them...
却又被那帮家伙如此糟践
For me, there's nothing left in such an island.
这样的岛还有什么好留恋的
Enough, I care no more...
够了 无所谓了
An apatheia!
απάθεια
Hey, she's a prisoner?
喂 这是俘虏吗？
Yep, we caught her.
是啊 咱们抓的
She is a soldier whose emotions have been taken away, and she's alive.
她是感情被抽走的士兵 还活着
Don't touch it!
不许碰
There's no need to treat guys without hearts as a human.
没有心灵的家伙没必要当人看
Whatever I do to it,
我爱对这家伙干什么…
or abandoning this island like a dishcloth,
我爱怎么抛弃这个抹布一样的破岛…
has nothing to do with you!
你们都管不着！
You are lying.
这是骗人的啊
Oni, you are not telling your real heart.
这不是欧尼你的真心
Your fellows died,
你失去了伙伴
and your dream and admiration for the world outside has been trashed.
失去了对外面的世界的梦想与憧憬
I do understand you feel hopeless.
我理解你丧失了希望
But I can see your true heart.
但是 我能看见你真正的心灵
You are...
你啊…
really willing to protect everybody.
其实是想保护好大家的
But you can't find a way, this fact pains you.
但是却不知道该怎么做 所以才会痛苦
Chakuro!
查克罗
Everybody is trying to decide what should we do.
你们一个个就知道对我们指手画脚
Don't make a decision without our own permissions!
我干什么不关你们事！
Chakuro, you should give up him.
查克罗 放弃他吧
If you put your time in dealing with that guy,
有这功夫跟他在这里磨叽
everybody will be sunk.
大家都一起沉到海底了
Let's go.
走吧
No, the vigilante group also guards here.
不行 这里也有警备团
After all, we know there's something underground.
果然地底下有什么东西
That's enough, let's break it through!
真麻烦 突破过去！
It's an emergency, forgive me.
非常时期 原谅我
Masoo you are so strong!
不愧是玛索
Don't forget I'm the man who ignored the scouts of the vigilante group!
我可是一脚踢开警备团的邀请的男人喔
So easy!
小菜一碟
However, I'm a little tired...
不过啊 稍微有点累了
Didn't you hear anything?
你们有没有听到什么声音
Shit, there are more inside.
该死 里面还有啊
You guys, help me!
你们俩 拜托了！
We are not familiar with the thymia.
我们平常不怎么用情念力的啊
That's why I hate the young Shirushi!
所以说最近的年轻印啊！
What?
咦
Chakky! What are you doing?
查奇♪ 干啥呢
Gin...
银…
What's that Chakky? How did you get that face?
怎么搞的啊查奇 怎么啦 瞧你这脸
What's up here?
怎么回事啊 这是
Th... This is...
这 这是…
What's up? You guys!
什么意思啊 你们
Miss!
姐姐！
Miss Ginshu!
银淑姐姐！
Dear Miss!
亲爱的姐姐！
I want to go inside!
我想到这里面去
Let me go! Dear Miss Ginshu!
让我过去！ 亲爱的银淑姐姐！
Hey Ginshu! This guy should...
喂 银淑！ 这家伙…
Uwa!
哇
Ginshu!
银淑
We are ordered to prevent people from entering the underground by the presbytery!
长老会不是命令我们谁都不让进地下的吗
I don't know the reason of their order.
长老会的命令不明就里
But what I understand well is...
但查奇的烦恼
My Chakky is in trouble!
我可是一清二楚！
This is all for my cute Chakky!
这全都是为了我可爱的查奇！
Hey, where's Chakky?
诶 咦 查奇呢？
Chakky!
查奇！
Chakky, when did you get so familiar with the vigilante?
查奇 你什么时候跟警备团这么熟了
I'm not Chakky!
别叫我查奇
Thank you, Ginshu.
银淑 谢谢
The captain!
团长！
Misfortunes never come alone...
这可是一波未平一波又起
That person is strong.
这个人 好强…
Of course!
那当然
Only those who are strong in their thymia can enter the vigilant group.
警备团是只有
And he's the top! The best!
而这是头头 当然是最强的人
No.1 in the mud whale!
在泥鲸是排第一的！
If he comes...
来的话…
Wh... What's that... Disappointing.
怎…怎么回事 真败兴子
Creepy...
毛骨悚然…
Well, that's fine. We are facing the internal area.
也罢 接下来就是体内区域了
We can no longer use thymia, so be careful.
用不了情念力 大家小心
As I thought, it's you.
果然 是你啊
You came to help those kids?
你是来支援他们的？
That's not somebody like you.
就说不像你
You are a bit troublesome.
你多少有些麻烦啊
I can't let you go~
不让你过
However...
的话
Come here!
过来
If you want to pass here...
想从这里过去的话
...let's play!
就陪你玩玩♪
Suddenly it becomes quiet.
突然安静了呢
Now we are facing the no-entry area.
这前面是不让进的区域了
Uwa!
哇
Where should Suo be arrested?
苏澳被关在哪里呢
Nezu and I will go around the prison and look for Suo.
我和涅兹去监狱里转一圈找苏澳
Leave it to us!
交给咱们
Suo has become our important chief, right?
苏澳已经是我们重要的首长了嘛
But how can you get him out...
但是 怎么从监狱里…
This.
这个
Made by the workshop, used to destroy the lock of prison.
工作室作品 破坏监狱门锁的道具
Hey, what the hell are you guys making!
你们俩 都做些什么东西啊！
The presbyters should be in the no-entry area.
长老会应该在禁止进入的区域里
We'll go ahead and investigate it. Join us later.
我们先去调查一下 一会汇合
All right!
嗯
Let's go.
走了
Don't you feel heavy?
不觉得空气很沉重么
Lykos...
黎可斯…
What is there over there?
这里有什么吗
What is the method to sink the mud whale?
让泥鲸沉没的方法到底是什么？
Hey Chakuro!
什么啊 查克罗
You brought us here but you don't even know that?
你不知道就把我们拖来了么
Sorry.
不好意思
Chakuro,
查克罗
you have already known it.
你已经知道了
You have touched that... at that time.
你那个时候…摸到过的东西
The light...
光…
The fourth section
第 四 节
We Shall Suicide in the Sand Together with the Mud Whale
第 四 节
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
Staring into the trace of the dried sea
眺望昔日的大海
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
I will draw the other side I have never seen
描绘未知的彼岸
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
If you remain your heart in captivity
如果囚禁起心灵  一如过往
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
You may live without knowing the pain
又怎会经历如此悲伤
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
The one who told the beautiful story
是谁讲述起美好的希望
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
Can not wait for the dawn
让我等不及黎明
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
Until beyond the end of world, I am swimming
向着天涯海角扬帆起航
虫の唄
虫の唄
Listen to the insects' song
彻夜虫鸣
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
That night is our memory
回忆里与你一起侧耳倾听
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
Just link hand in hand
只是双手相牵
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
No matter it is twilight or a distant country
不论夕阳  还是远方
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
Born in a short chapter
在这短暂苍渺的一章里
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう
But let us go and embrace that dream
一起追逐梦想
The fifth section
第 五 节
I don't want to run away from the hope
不 想 逃 避 希 望